What are we?
קפ"ד, Kuf Yud Daled, ק"י, Kuf Yud, קפ"ד, Kuf Yud Daled, 110.
Ah, that was a pop quiz. Okay, so we've started the very
bottom line of ק"י עמוד ב'. Kuf Yud Amud Bet. Just to
warn everybody that we are still, we are not leaving the world
of demons today. Okay, so let's take a look. We pick up
at the very bottom line of ק"י עמוד ב'. Kuf Yud Amud
Bet. We have been discussing pairs and how pairs make you susceptible
either to מזיקין mazikin or to witchcraft if people are practicing witchcraft
in your neighborhood. All right, and the Gemara spoke about what constitutes,
you know, when can you combine things so that you get an
odd number as opposed to an even, and drinking before the meal
and during the meal, so we really just left off one line
about that. So the Gemara says two lines from the bottom after
the parentheses, דכולי
עלמא תרי אטאקא וחד לבתר אטאקא לא מצטרפי. dechulei alma trei attaka
ve-chad levatar attaka lo mitztarfei. Everybody would agree that two cups of
wine, glasses of wine during the meal and one after the meal
do not combine, so you can't add that to make three and
to get you out of trouble.
Like the story of Rava bar Nachmani, interesting when the Gemara always
in the Gemara refers to itself, this is a story that is
in בבא מציעא Bava Metzia where he drank during the meal and
then they removed the plate or the table and he wanted a
drink to get out of pairs and he insisted that they bring
the plate or the table back. So because he insisted they bring
the table back, you see that the drinking after the meal would
not combine with the drinking during the meal. Okay, moving up. אמר
רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, כל המזוג מצטרף.
kol hamazug mitztaref. All types of mixed drinks combine because, you know,
they would mix their wine with water as we knew. You'd have
other types of things that you would mix with water, so even
though some are wine and some are not wine and we discussed
wine and beer, any type of mixed drink is considered to be
enough of the same category that it can combine and get you
out of the pairs if you have like a two and a
one type of a combination. חוץ מן המים, Chutz min hamayim, exception
of water. Now you're saying wait, water is not a mixed drink?
Ah, but we will see that they would sometimes mix hot water
with cold water, presumably to cool it off or to heat it
up. I don't know if they had any other thoughts that the
act of mixing had some effect. But even if you do that,
since it's all water, it doesn't constitute a mixed drink or
a, you know, a watered drink. Maybe is the more accurate term
of the word מזוג. mazug. Not like we would call like, you
know, like
orange juice and vodka is not a mixed drink for the Gemara.
I don't think so. It's basically mixing it with water. רבי יוחנן
אמר, Rabbi Yochanan amar, now Rabbi Yochanan who comes from ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael will remember that at least the Gemara was saying that
in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael they don't buy into this at all.
Anyway, here maybe he's buying into it somewhat or anyway, he says
אפילו מים, afilu mayim, even water can count as a mixed drink
to help combine. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa, לא אמרן אלא,
lo amran ela, we didn't say this except what constitutes a mixed
drink of
water, חמימי לגו קרירי וקרירי לגו חמימי, chamimi lego kriri ve-kriri lego
chamimi, hot water mixed into cold or cold water mixed into hot,
so there's some difference in terms of the qualities of the waters
that you're mixing together, two types of water. אבל חמימי לגו חמימי,
aval chamimi lego chamimi, if you pour hot water into hot, maybe
you're just adding water or maybe, you know, one is hotter than
the other and you're trying to heat one up a little bit
more like you know you get your, you know, your tea has
cooled down a little bit but it's still hot, but you add
more hot water to get it
hotter, וקרירי לגו קרירי ve-kriri lego kriri or cold water you add
to cold water, לא. lo. That, that would still be different enough
that they would not, that they would not be, that they would
not be considered mixed and it would not combine with other mixed
drinks. אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, said Reish Lakish. ארבעה דברים
העושה אותן דמו בראשו, arba'a devarim ha'oseh otan damo berosho, four things
if you do them, you know, your blood is on your own
hands, you're exposing yourself to mortal
danger, ומתחייב בנפשו. u-mitchayev benafsho. Interesting double language, דמו בראשו damo berosho
ומתחייב בנפשו, u-mitchayev benafsho, seems like it's the same point. Anyway, what
are these four things? אלו הן, elu hen, these are they: הנפנה
בין דקל לכותל, ha-nifneh bein dekel le-kotel, if you relieve yourself, between
talking particularly about defecate, between the a palm tree and a wall
because presumably as we're about to see, that would be a place
where שדים shedim would go. So you're and you're, well no, the
space between a palm tree and a wall, this narrow space, and
there's no place for the שד shed to avoid you, so you're
asking for him to bump into you.
So because he's also got to walk and get from place to
place, okay, presumably they walk, they don't fly at it sounds like
here in this Gemara as we'll see.
ועובר בין שני דקלים, ve-over bein shnei dekalim, or if you pass
between two palm trees, also presumably a preferred path for the שדים
shedim to be walking.
ושותה מים שאולים, ve-shoteh mayim she'ulim, if you drink borrowed water as
we'll find out, the שדים shedim are also need to
drink as Michael provided us with this book here on Jewish magic
and superstition, quoting a רש"י Rashi who to who portrays שדים shedim
as a subset of
מזיקין mazikin and this is actually רש"י, Rashi, this line is from
the Gemara but I just have it in front of me: שדים
shedim have human forms and eat and drink like men.
So here we're going to see that they need to drink. So
they drink water and presumably maybe they have more ability
to access borrowed water, it's more sort of vulnerable to that to
their, you know, to their powers. So therefore if you're drinking from
borrowed water, you might be in competition with the shade, not good
business, not a good idea. ואובר על מים שפוכין, V'over al mayim
shfuchin, and if you walk over spilled water, presumably that's also a
place where a shade will hang out. ואפילו שפכתה אשתו בפניו, V'afilu
shafchata ishto befanav, even if you could say look, I know where
the provenance of this water, you know, my wife spilled it out
and I was watching, so nothing, you know, it's all been observed,
I know where it came from, doesn't matter, once it's spilled water,
presumably it's a place potentially of
שדים. Shedim. Now, now we're going to unpack this and analyze this.
הנפנה בין דקל לכותל, Hanifneh bein dekel lekotel, somebody who relieves himself
between the wall and a palm tree. לא אמרן, Lo amran, this
is only true, אלא דלית ליה ארבע אמות, Ela d'leit lei arba
amot, that there's not four אמות, Amot, presumably it means not just
four אמות Amot between the palm tree and the wall, but four
אמות Amot outside of the space that you're sitting, giving enough space
for the shade to pass through. אבל אית ליה ארבע אמות, Aval
it lei arba amot, but if you do have four אמות, Amot,
then they the shade can pass through, so we're not it's not,
even if the shade is going that way, we'll assume that, you
know, ideally he'll leave you alone, you leave him alone. It's only
like, it's sort of like you know what they say like, you
know, bees on, no, reminds me because of סוכות Sukkot reminds me
like you know the whole you know the bees, right? You know
the key is just ignore them, leave them alone, they won't bother
you. It's like the גמרא, Gemara, if you're מקפיד, Makpid, they'll be
מקפיד, Makpid, right? So leave them alone, they won't bother you, don't
force a confrontation. Okay, so anyway,
okay, so that's only if there's not four אמות. Amot. אבל אית
ליה ארבע אמות, Aval it lei arba amot, if the, if there
is four אמות, Amot, לית לן בה, Leit lan bah, it's not
a problem, the shade will go in the space you've left for
him. וכי לית ליה ארבע אמות, V'chi leit lei arba amot, even
if there's not four אמות, Amot, לא אמרן, Lo amran, it's not
a problem, אלא דליכא דרכא אחרינא, Ela d'leika darchah achrinah, only if
there's no alternative alternate path. If there's other paths, then the shade
will take the other path, he's not going to bother you. Okay,
אלא איכא דרכא אחרינא, Ela ika darchah achrinah, if there's another path,
לית לן בה, Leit lan bah, it's not a problem. That's the
relieving yourself. והאובר בין שני דקלים, V'haover bein shnei dekalim, going between
two palm trees, passing between two palm trees. Interesting, you know, the
idea is you're getting in the way of the shade, why one
is about relieving yourself and the other is about walking, I really
don't know. Anyway, if you walk between two palm trees, לא אמרן
אלא דלא פסקינהו רשות הרבים, Lo amran ela d'la paskin'hu reshut harabim,
that's only if a public thoroughfare has not passed through them, because
שדים Shedim will avoid the masses. אבל פסקינהו רשות הרבים, Aval paskin'hu
reshut harabim, if a public thoroughfare passes through it, לית לן בה,
Leit lan bah, it's not a problem. Again, you know, these issues
between a palm tree and a wall, you're going there for privacy,
you have to relieve yourself, but presumably the שדים Shedim prefer the
darker places, I know there's a dark one going back to the
other one, prefer the darker places, prefer the places that there are
not many people, and therefore here where it's a question of walking
between these trees, if it's a public place, it's not a problem,
if it's a public thoroughfare. השואל מים שאולים, Hashoel mayim sheulim, drinking
borrowed water, לא אמרן, Lo amran, it's only true, אלא דשאילינהו קטן,
Ela d'shailinhu katan, only if a minor borrowed them. Maybe a minor
borrowed them he wasn't able to watch them as well and somehow
again it exposed them. אבל גדול לית לן בה, Aval gadol leit
lan bah, borrowed from an adult, it's not a problem. I really
don't know what to say about that.
ואפילו שאילינהו קטן, V'afilu shailinhu katan, even if a minor borrowed them,
נמי לא אמרן, Nami lo amran, we also didn't say this, it's
also not true, אלא בשדה, Ela basadeh, only if you're drinking this
water and it's out in a field where water is not easily
available, דלא שכיחי, D'la shechichi, that water is not available, so you
and the shade will be competing for the water. אבל בעיר, Aval
ba'ir, if you're in a city, דשכיחי, D'shechichi, that there's a lot
of water available, there's a lot of wells, so לית לן בה,
Leit lan bah, it's not a problem, the shade will always get
his water from somewhere else. Of course somewhere else may be somebody
else's drink, but anyway maybe he'll go straight to the well, I
don't know. But anyway if there's a lot of water available you
don't have to worry about it. ואפילו בשדה נמי לא אמרן, V'afilu
basadeh nami lo amran, and we also didn't say this in a
field, אלא מיא, Ela maya, it's only water. אבל חמרא ושכרא, Aval
chamra v'shichra, wine and beer, לית לן בה, Leit lan bah, we're
not worried about it. So the shade is very health conscious, he
only drinks water, okay, so therefore he's not a concern. Although if
you drink multiple cups of wine you expose yourself, but that's not
because you're competing for the water, that's just because doing pairs endangers
you, whereas here it's actually competing for it and the shade is
only interested in the water. והאובר על מים שפוכין, V'haover al mayim
shfuchin, if you pass over
spilled water, לא אמרן, Lo amran, we didn't say it, אלא דלא
אפסיקינהו בעפרא, Ela d'la afsikinhu be'afra, that's only if you didn't interrupt
them, I mean like you didn't put on them some dirt. Okay,
so and ולא טף בהו רוקא, V'la taf behu ruka, you didn't
spit in it.
Are you going to drink spit?
No, you're not drinking, you're walking, you're stepping over a puddle, or
not a puddle, you're stepping over some spilled water, you know, they
didn't have plumbing, so they would, so whatever water they'd, the dirty
water they'd use for their dishes, or maybe the water they would
use for their bathroom or whatever, afterwards you would just go and
spill it out. soiled water mostly is what we're talking about when
we're talking about שופכין. Shufchin. It's not just you happen to spill
a glass of water, it's soiled water. Okay? So maybe also the
stench or whatever. Something is it that attracts the שדים. Shedim. But
if you do something to change it, maybe make it more like
the ground, maybe make it more dilute, so you put a little
dirt in it or you spit in it, then it's not a
problem. אבל הפסיקנו, Avel hifsiknu, if you interrupt it, meaning with dirt,
you put some dirt in it, או טף בו רוק, o taf
bo rok, or you spit in it, לית לן בה, leit lan
bah, it's not a problem. ולא אמרן אלא דלא עבר עלייהו שמשא,
Velo amran ela dela avar aleihu shimsha, and all this is also
when it's very fresh, this dirty water, this
sewage is a way of maybe thinking about it. But if the
sun has passed over it, maybe means a day has passed, or
I don't know, maybe it means it's just been exposed to sunlight.
ולא עבר עלייהו שתין ניגרי, Velo avar aleihu shittin nigrei, or sixty
steps have not stepped over it. So if other people have exposed
themselves, then you're okay.
אבל עבר עלייהו שמשא, Avel avar aleihu shimsha, once the sun has
passed over it, ועבר עלייהו שתין ניגרי, ve-avar aleihu shittin nigrei, or
sixty steps have walked over it, לית לן בה, leit lan bah,
it's not a problem. ולא אמרן אלא דלא רכיב חמרא ולא סיים
מסאני, Velo amran ela dela rachiv chamra velo sayim masanei, and all
even when it is a problem, it's only if you're not riding
a donkey and not wearing shoes. So it's a question whether it
means both or or, but we read it as or, if you're
not directly walking over it with your bare feet. Either you're wearing
shoes or you're on a donkey, then that's also not a problem.
אבל רכיב חמרא וסיים מסאני, Avel rachiv chamra vesayim masanei, but if
you're riding a donkey and/or wearing shoes, לית לן בה, leit lan
bah, not a problem. והני מילי, Vehani milei, all of this, presumably
everything we said, but certainly the last one, but maybe everything that
these are sort of ways in which these issues aren't a problem—the
palm trees, the water,
etc.—היכא דליכא למיחש לכשפים. heicha deleika lemichash lechshafim. That only gets you
away from the שדים Shedim when they're acting sort of, you know,
just doing their normal travels in the world, the מזיקין. mazikin. And
you don't have to worry about people practicing witchcraft. אבל היכא דאיכא
למיחש לכשפים, Avel heicha de-ika lemichash le-chshafim, but in a place where
there are people practicing witchcraft and somebody is directing witchcraft towards you,
אף על גב דאיכא כל הני, af al gav de-ika kol hanei,
even though you have protected yourself in all these various ways to
get around these particular dangers of the water and of the palm
tree and whatnot, חיישינן, chaishinan, nevertheless, you are still—you still have to
be concerned. It is interesting, the גמרא'ס Gemara's assumption that it is
the same phenomena that expose you to the dangers of שדים Shedim
that also make you susceptible to the dangers of the witchcraft, right?
I mean, why should that be true? You know, whatever they believe,
but could be very different types of things make you susceptible—interestingly susceptible—to
שדים. Shedim. So I do wonder, again, I'm sure there's a lot
of research out there, I just haven't—don't know it, about the assumption
of whether the witchcraft draws on the שדים Shedim for it to
have its effect. You know, is there some intersection between the world
of witchcraft and the world of שדים, Shedim, that those are the
powers that are being drawn upon? I don't know, but it's interesting
that it's the same types of things that expose you to witchcraft
if witchcraft is being practiced, and actually once it's being practiced, even
if you take these precautions, it does not do you any good.
דההוא גברא, De-hahu gavra, like that person, דהוה רכיב חמרא וסיים מסאני,
de-hava rachiv chamra vesayim masanei, he was wearing—he was on his donkey,
he was wearing shoes, and presumably parenthetically somebody was doing witchcraft against
him, וגמד מסאניה וצוו כרעיה, ve-gamud masaneih vetzavu kreiyeh, and his shoes
shriveled and his leg withered. So presumably the only explanation is is
that because he went over water and even though he took these
precautions, he went over spilled water, must be somebody was doing witchcraft
against him. Okay, yes.
I just have to say a short positive thing. Please.
It's all positive, it's positive ways of avoiding these problems. Anyway, go
ahead, yes.
So I just want to note, it is very striking
that their world was a world that was dynamic and filled with
animate beings. Right.
That so the world was very personalized in a way. It was
physical and non-physical, so to speak, whereas our—we cope with making sense
of reality with a deep sense of the randomness at the center
and an impersonality and a smallness. So although it's hard to wrap
your mind around the superstition,
right, they
live in a world that's very personal and direct
and
it's interesting, I hear what you're saying, although I wouldn't have described
the difference as personal versus random, you know, I would have described
it as materialist versus spiritual, meaning, you know, that they have all
of these non-physical material forces which, you know, in terms of what
it does for, look, you know, obviously people say, you know, religion
and superstition, you know, and so on, but you know, what it
does to cultivate a sense of something beyond the physical world. But
I don't know if that's about being personal, something beyond the physical
world where for us we live in a much more I would
say, you know, it's lonely because there's no sense of
anything.
No one here in this worldview, no one's gonna say why me?
Well, right, it happened to you because you walked over the puddle
without.
Right, right, right, right. Okay,
alright, alright, I hear, I hear, I hear. It's a very good
point, and the question is about it's true when you sort
of live in a rationalist religious mentality,
there's what's sort of sacrificed in terms of a power
of the metaphysical and a power. So I agree. It's a very
good point. Yes.
Is there an explanation why there's such power?
I don't know. Yeah, about what exactly it is about pairs. Yeah,
I don't.
Right.
Well right, that's what we said yesterday because as if you're מחמיר,
machmir, right, if you believe in it then it becomes more of
a reality or a reality we would say. Alright, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this. Okay, תנו
רבנן, Tanoo Rabbanan, now we get to I think very challenging גמרא.
Gemara. תנו רבנן שלושה אין ממצעין ולא מתמצעין. Tanoo Rabbanan shlosha ain
mimetzin velo mitmetzin.
There are three
entities, people, whatever, animals that you do not ממצעין mimetzin allow them
to become middle, you don't let them be middles, meaning that if
there're two people on the side you don't let this thing come
in the middle. ולא מתמצעין velo mitmetzin which is reflexive, you don't
allow yourself to be between two of them. So you don't allow
one of them to be between two people and you or two
of you, and you don't allow yourself to be between two of
them. What are these three? ואלו הן הכלב והדקל והאשה. ve-eilu hein
hakelev vehadekel veha'isha. So obviously very disturbing גמרא, Gemara, dogs, palm
trees, we obviously because we mentioned two palm trees, and women. Again,
is this because of their שדים shedim idea? What is the concern
here? Let's read a little more. ויש אומרים אף החזיר. ve-yeish omrim
af hachazir. Some say even a pig. ויש אומרים אף הנחש ve-yeish
omrim af hanachash and some say even a serpent, a snake. ואם
ממצעין מאי תקנתיה? ve-im mimetzin mai takantei? And if you came between
or they came between you, what's the way of fixing it?
So protecting yourself apparently from the forces that are stirred up when
these things happen. So אמר רב פפא, amar Rav Papa, נפתח באל
ונסיים באל, niftach b'El venisayem b'El, either you start a פסוק pasuk
with אל El and you end with אל, El, God's name. אי
נמי נפתח בלא ונסיים בלא, inami niftach belo venisayem belo, or you
start with לא lo and you end with לא. lo. What does
this mean? So the רשב"ם Rashbam says, I think probably quoting רש"י,
Rashi, haven't checked רש"י, Rashi, but yes, רש"י. Rashi. So רש"י Rashi
says,
אל מוציאם ממצרים כתועפות ראם לו כי לא נחש ביעקב ולא קסם
בישראל כעת יאמר ליעקב ולישראל מה פעל אל. El motziam mimitzrayim kito'afot
re'eim lo ki lo nachash beya'akov velo kessem beyisrael ka'et ye'ameir leya'akov
uleyisrael mah pa'al El. So it's actually a פסוק pasuk that opens
with אל El and ends with אל. El. Now לא lo of
the curse of Bilaam.
Right. That right. So it is, it's a world that
evokes curses and use of other powers
and כי לא נחש, ki lo nachash, it's a very powerful phrase,
right, because it's לא נחש ביעקב ולא קסם בישראל. lo nachash beya'akov
velo kessem beyisrael. It's about witchcraft not having a power. So that's
a very powerful פסוק pasuk because also because it also it makes
אל El like the whole thing is about
sandwiching, that you sandwich something or something sandwiched, you were between these
two things, it was between you, so here you're having אל El
sandwiching you as it were, you being in the middle of the
פסוק pasuk of אל El on both sides and it's
about witchcraft doesn't have the power. The לא lo is a little
bit harder, he quotes the פסוק לא איש אל ויכזב ובן אדם
ויתנחם ההוא אמר ולא יעשה ודבר ולא
יקימנה. pasuk lo ish El veyichazev uben adam veyitnecham hahu amar velo
ya'aseh vedibeir velo yekimena. So it starts close, there's לא lo and
לא lo although it ends with a word after the לא. lo.
But again, very appropriate as we can see multiple ways in which
it refers to this. תוספות Tosafot is bothered by this, if you
look at תוספות Tosafot he says פירוש רשב"ם, peirash Rashbam, it's interesting
because רש"י Rashi also says it. פירוש רשב"ם אל מוציאם ממצרים ונפתח
בלא לא איש אל ויכזב. peirash Rashbam El motziam mimitzrayim veniftach belo
lo ish El veyichazev. Now he's got a problem. ואף על גב
דאסור להתרפאות בדברי תורה, ve'af al gav de'assur lehitrapot bedivrei Torah, you're
not allowed to use תורה Torah as a way of curing yourself,
you're not supposed to turn תורה Torah into some type of. Oh
yeah, okay, so that's a whole discussion, but you're not supposed to
use
תורה Torah for these like you can pray, you use prayer,
you turn to God and ask God for healing, but it's not
like you don't want to have the תורה Torah be like this
magic and this incantation. So he's got a couple of answers. Let's
see what his answers are.
So it's the גמרא, Gemara, the עין יעקב Ein Yaakov gives you
the reference, שבועות ט"ו ע"ב. Shevuot tet-vav amud-bet. Okay, so he says
להגן שרי. lehagen shari. First, well, he says look, you're not healing
yourself, you're just protecting
yourself. That's happened to you yet, so it's just preventative. But again,
how that's exactly the problem, I'm not exactly clear to me. Okay,
now we've got another issue. והא דאמר בפרק במה אשה ve-ha d'amar
b'perek bameh isha in שבת, Shabbos, לאשתא צמירתא לשקול צמיחת סכינא le-ishta
tzimira lishkol tzmichas sachina ולימא ויאמר משה אסורה נא ואראה את, ve-leima
vayomer Moshe asura na ve-ere es, so he has another גמרא Gemara
that talks about saying a פסוק pasuk when you're trying to heal
some type of a fever. So why is that allowed? So he
says משום סכנה שרי. mishum sakana shari. So, if it's a life-threatening
thing that's allowed, and preventative that's allowed, but if it's an illness
that's not life-threatening then you don't use תורה. Torah. But again, as
Michael says, this does point to this whole issue, you know, and
it does get to this world of demons and what we're talking
about in a world which is filled with these powers, then the
other issue is how do you protect yourself from these powers? You
know, so the גמרא, Gemara, the גמרא Gemara in a will refer
to amulets in a minute. We know that incantations and amulets was
a major part of that world. And then it gets to the
problem of what it does to pervert תורה, Torah, that תורה Torah
then becomes a type of a magic and not its, you know,
and you know, the relationship to God is not is one more
of magic than it is one of prayer and מעשים טובים maasim
tovim and מצות mitzvos and so on. So you see here תוספות
Tosafos obviously grappling with that. And now it's interesting though, because of
that problem he offers a completely different explanation. רבנו חננאל פירש Rabbeinu
Chananel peirush that you don't use פסוקים, psukim, it's a תפילה, tefillah,
a תפילה tefillah that opens with אל El and ends with אל
El or opens with לא lo and ends with לא. lo. And
it's very beautiful, he writes a new תפילה. tefillah. Let's see what
the תפילה tefillah is. באל לימא הכי, be-El leima hachi, אל אלהים
ה' הצילני מכל רע מכל נזק אשר בידך כח וגבורה כי אתה
אל. El Elohim Hashem hatzileni mikol ra mikol nezek asher beyadka koach
ugevurah ki atah El. Okay, nice little תפילה tefillah that opens with
אל El and ends with אל El and is a תפילה, tefillah,
God protect us. ונפתח בלא, ve-niftach be-lo, לא תתחני אלהי, lo titecheni
Elohai, do not abandon me, ולא תעזבני שמרני כאישון בת עין טרם
אקרא תענני ואל תאמר לא. ve-lo ta'azveni shamreni k'ishon bat ayin terem
ekra ta'aneni ve'al tomar lo. Answer me and don't say no. So
it ends with לא. lo. Okay, but he's he likes he creates
some alternatives. Now of course the problem here with this is the
introduction of the woman because it's one thing that you have all
these issues and all these superstitions but then how that goes ahead
and impacts, you know, the way in which either it's a reflection
of or a or a furthering of, you know, or an encouragement
to view, you know, to view women, fifty percent of society in
a way that they have these potential, you know, even if they're
not, first of all, we just got through them being the witch,
you know, the association of them with witchcraft and witchcraft being a
regular assumption here that that's an ever-present problem. And now, even maybe
because of the witchcraft issue, we'll see another thing in a minute,
the assumption again of the just sort of like an ever-present danger
with them. So you know you're on the street and there's a
woman all of a sudden you have to worry about how you're
going to be walking, you know, with her and around her and
so on. So obviously this, you know, is very disturbing in terms
of, again, a reflection and a furthering of a way in which
society looks, you know, looks at women. So let's read a little
bit more about this in the גמרא, Gemara, it's not going to
get better. So let's take a look. Wait, I want to just
read a little one more thing and then they'll say הני בי
תרי דמצוע להו אשה נדה, hani bei tere de-matzu'ah lehu isha nidda,
if two people have a נדה, niddah, a woman who's a נדה
niddah pass between them. So before we were talking about it said
just woman, maybe this is coming to limit it to this, a
נדה niddah passed between them. אם תחלת נדתה היא, im techilas niddasah
hi, if it's the beginning of the period of her flow, of
her of her of her period, of her menstruation, הורגת אחת מהן,
horegas achas mehen, then that'll kill one of them. ואם סוף נדתה
היא, ve-im sof niddasah hi, if it's the end of this period,
מריבה עושה ביניהן, meriva osa beineihen, it leads them to fight, you
know, to fight with one another. מאי תקנתיה, mai takantei, what do
they do to fix this to protect themselves from this? נפתח באל
ונסיים באל, niftach be-El ve-nisayeim be-El, the same thing about the אל,
El, I don't know, maybe not the לא. lo. Okay, so here
we get also the specific issue about נדה. niddah. Now what's fascinating
we're learning נדה niddah this year in the ישיבה, Yeshiva, it's quite
clear that in in ancient societies there were taboos around women who
were who were menstruating, they had to live apart from, you know,
the male society, they had to leave, you know, leave the home,
they couldn't touch food, they would contaminate the food, if they breathed
on you it would be a danger. There were it's clear even
in some societies today, you know, this still, you know, in developing
countries this still plays out, and it has a profound, you know,
and devastating impact, you know, because women who are living apart from
the male society are also vulnerable to rape and whatever, there's a
lot of very bad stuff around that. But anyway, in the תורה
Torah you don't find that at all, the תורה Torah treats נדה
niddah just as a טומאה tumah and איסור עריות, issur arayos, does
not treat it any way any different.
And the גמרא Gemara completely ignores that in the מסכת נדה Masechet
Niddah and all of its discussion. The whole issues of separation of
husband and wife during the נדה niddah period are just straight concerns
about sex, not about anything beyond this some type of a taboo
or power. The גמרא, Gemara, you know, very powerfully and says that
a husband and wife when the woman is a נדה niddah is
a נדה niddah sleep in the same bedroom. room and A they're
not concerned about normal ייחוד Yichud with a woman a man can't
have sex with and B complete rejection of any sense of this
casting the woman out. It is interesting that the Ethiopian Jews, right,
had the practice of the women when they were נדה Niddah sleeping
in a different place. So the גמרא Gemara in its הלכתי Halakhic
discussion ignores these concerns and clearly פוסקן Paskens in ways that are
just straight הלכה Halakhah issues, ways that completely contravene any of this
type of an attitude. Nevertheless, there's a גמרא Gemara which is much
less about, not a הלכתי Halakhic discussion, but seems to reflect this
reality of this perception that people would have about the powers, the
negative powers that might surround a woman when she is נדה. Niddah.
Now תוספות Tosafot mitigates it a little bit. תוספות Tosafot says: יש
מפרש אם עושה להן כישוף, Yesh Mefareish im oseh lahen Kishuf, that
maybe again tying into not women in general but specifically a concern
of witchcraft. So maybe a woman who's a נדה Niddah who's actively
doing witchcraft against them, maybe somehow those combine to have some impact.
So again it makes it somewhat better that it doesn't become a
blanket perception, but nevertheless if you're always afraid of women doing witchcraft,
I don't know how much better it really makes it. But these
are really definitely disturbing גמרות. Gemaros. Dov wanted to say something.
No, I was just simply, the ר"ח Rach is really interesting because
the ר"ח Rach then you have both possibilities, יש אומרים Yesh Omrim
the פסוקים Psukim and יש אומרים Yesh Omrim this תפילה. Tefilla.
Right. Well the ר"ח Rach doesn't give you both possibilities. תוספות Tosafot
gives you both.
No the ר"ח Rach gives you both.
Oh in the רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel itself? Oh I didn't read
it.
No the תוספות, Tosafot, oh you're right.
The ר"ח Rach has both the פסוקים Psukim or the
תפילה, Tefilla, as if the ר"ח Rach just has the תפילה.
Tefilla. I didn't check. You're right, but the ר"ח Rach actually quotes
both possibilities, yes.
To the academics, make any suggestion that
maybe these are from completely different traditions, completely different ישיבות? Yeshivahs?
Yeah, I mean, in general the whole issue about all of these,
it's a good question, right? Because the גמרא Gemara said before that
this is, the גמרא Gemara itself said this is a concern in
בבל, Bovel, not in
ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisroel. But there's also a question like who exactly
is saying all this stuff? So much of this is like the
סתם, Stam, is not named אמוראים, Amoraim, right? And now every now
and then like רבי יוחנן אמר אפילו מים. Rabbi Yochanan amar afilla
mayim. What context was he saying that in? Right? I mean Halivni
thinks that very often the גמרא Gemara takes a statement of an
אמורא Amora and will get the context wrong. He could have said
אפילו מים afilla mayim about a hundred different things, right? The גמרא
Gemara is assuming that, I mean I think that that's sometimes a
little radical, those types of assertions that Halivni makes, but nevertheless, the
amount here of this material is אמוראי, Amoraic, is סתמאית, Stama'it, is
the סתם Stam of the גמרא. Gemara. So how much do we
assume that these types of attitudes were widely held by the other
אמוראים? Amoraim? And who exactly were the ones expressing these issues? I
think that that's an excellent question. Rifka.
I think we shouldn't skip over the fact that these attitudes crept
into daily life and for centuries women were kept away from ספרי
תורה. Sifrei Torah. Today they still are, in most בתי כנסת Batei
Knesset though.
Right
and you're absolutely correct. Look, in the time, although the גמרא Gemara
other than like this passage, in all its הלכתי Halakhic discussion ignores
it, the many ראשונים Rishonim and there was clearly a popular conception
that had these types of concerns that treated women during their נדה
Niddah period when they were bleeding differently than when they were not
bleeding even though they were still נדות. Niddos. And that, and that,
and there was a work out called
ברייתא דמסכת נדה, Baraita De-Massechet Niddah, which the רמב"ן Ramban others thought
was like a really תנאי Tannaitic or whatever, early. It's very questionable
who wrote it, some think it's a קראי Karaitic work and so
on. And that work is filled with these taboos about women making
food and touching food and all saying ברכות, Brochos, reading from סידור.
Siddur. And yes, and in אשכנז Ashkenaz in particular there developed this
issue about women not going to, even more than that, not going
to שול, Shul, not reading from a סידור. Siddur. The question was,
can a woman go to שול Shul on יום כיפור Yom Kippur
because it would be really hard for her, not women in general
but women when they were נדה, Niddah, right? Can they be doing,
can they engage in any sense of connecting with the holy? And
I agree with you, look at it, right, absolutely. And some of
these things definitely came, were there at the popular level and came
up in the הלכתי Halakhic discussion in the Middle Ages, and it's
definitely an issue, yes.
In the modern period too, I mean, it's really not much different
than today where you have on one hand people are committed to
a הלכה Halakhah which is intellectual and logical and so on. These
same people wear red strings
and many believe in these things, in these powers, for sure. At
the same time, logical, intellectual, I see them all the time. Me
too.
Yeah,
I mean the רמב"ם Rambam was particularly concerned about it around מזוזה
Mezuzah and people writing names of angels on מזוזות. Mezuzos. you know,
yeah, I mean I once went to somebody's house who lived in
a in a like community in in a little place like here
in Riverdale but whatever that had a private road and it had
a you know like eight houses or whatever around and it had
a like gate in front of the road and I was going
and I saw there's no מזוזה mezuzah on the gate and basically
everybody who lived there was Jewish, you know, so it's a perfect
קיום kiyum of like בשעריך. Bisharecha. So I said to someone I
said, you know, you needed a, you know, you need a מזוזה
mezuzah there. So later I heard that this person came and said,
yeah, you know, yeah, whatever, he said I asked the שאלה, sheilah,
I said, do I need a מזוזה? mezuzah? He says, it'll be
good, it'll help protect us anyway. So, I'm talking הלכה בשעריך, halachah
bisharecha, oh well, whatever, it'll protect us anyway. It's a סגולה, segulah,
right? So, anyway, but yeah, this serious issue about how some of
these things become, you know, amulet type of powers rather than a
more, you know, rationalist approach to תורה Torah and מצוות. mitzvos. So,
yeah.
What was that word that you mentioned?
A ברייתא דמסכת נדה? braita deMasechet Niddah? It's on
I can get it to you as a PDF I mean you
get it you you know, it's not in a normal book, you
know, it's not in a normal בית מדרש beis medrash but it's
a you know it's been an academic sort of addition has been
put out.
And it was found at the manuscript in manuscript?
Yeah, I mean the ראשונים Rishonim quote it, so it's not like
it was somebody just discovered it. I don't know how many manuscripts
we have of it, but the ראשונים Rishonim like the רמב"ן Ramban
quotes from it.
Not reprinted anywhere in the normal like like I
think you might be able to get it, you know, on like
a the PDF might be available online, and if not I have
one, you know, so yeah.
Right, it's called ברייתא דמסכת נדה.
braita deMasechet Niddah.
Okay. So, you know now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay. So, that was interesting.
Now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay. Okay, נפתח באלף ונשתך באלף. Niftach b'aleph venishtach b'aleph. הני תרי
נשי יתבן בפרשת דרכים. Hanei trei nashei yatvan b'parashat drachim.
So back to women.
Two women who are sitting at a crossroads. וחדא בהאי גיסא דשבילא
וחדא באידך גיסא. V'chada b'hai gisa dishvila v'chada b'idach gisa.
One on one side of the road and the other on the
other side of the road. ומכוונן אפייהו להדדי, Umichavnan apailei hadadi, and
they're facing one another. So you're walking down a road and you
see two women looking at one another sitting on opposite sides of
the road. ודאי בכשפים עסקינן. Vada'i b'kshafim askinan. So clearly that is
a position they would be taking because they're involved in doing some
witchcraft. מאי תקנתיה? Mai takantei? So what should you do if you
pass them? Now you're being exposed to the witchcraft. אי איכא דרכא
אחרינא ליזיל בה. Ieka darcha achrina, leizil bah. First good advice. If
there's another road, take it. Like as the Yogi Berra says, when
you come to a fork in the road, take it. ואי ליכא
דרכא אחרינא, V'ee leka darcha achrina,
if there's no other path, אי איכא אינש אחרינא בהדיה, eeka inash
achrina bahadei, if you have somebody else with you, נינקטו לידיהו בהדי
הדדי ninqtu leyadaihu bahadei hadadi וניחלסון v'nechlusun pass through. ואי ליכא אינש
אחרינא, V'ee leka inash achrina,
and if there's nobody else with you, נימא הכי, neima hachi, say
the following: אגרת אזלת אסיה בלוסיא מתקטלא בחיק טבל. Igeret azlat asya
blusya mitkatla b'cheik tevel.
So there's some incantation, the first words are presumably names of demonic
powers, אגרת אזלת אסיה בלוסיא, Igeret azlat asya blusya, and מתקטלא בחיק
טבל mitkatla b'cheik tevel basically means you should get, you know, sort
of piercing murderous arrows should you know should go into you. So
that's what you say to them. Okay. You're cursing them to protect
yourself. But right, it's like the גמרא Gemara before that had a
little incantation curse right about your, you know, about all your witchcraft
should blow away and when you when you chain two women doing
witchcraft. You're cursing the שד. shed. Well, you're cursing the שדים sheidim
or you're cursing the women? Well, maybe the שדים. sheidim. No, no,
no, the שדים sheidim are what you mentioned. אגרת אזלת אסיה בלוסיא
Agras Azlas Asya Blusya are the names of שדים. sheidim.
So yeah, the רשב"ם Rashbam seems to say that. It says מתקטלין
בחיק טבל, mitkatlim b'cheik tevel, like six lines from the bottom he
says, כבר הרוגין הם בחצים, k'tzar harugin heim b'chitzim, הם heim presumably
meaning these these witchcraft, these שדים sheidim are already should already be,
you know, killed with arrows. Or are already killed, right. Okay. Alright,
anyway, so that's so that's what you do. Now. האי מאן דפגע
באיתתא בעידנא דסלקא מטבילת מצוה, Hai man d'paga b'it-teta b'idna d'salka mitvilas
mitzvah, so back to נדה Niddah related issues. A person who bumps
into a woman at the moment that she is coming out of
the מקוה, mikvah,
טבילת מצוה tvilas mitzvah right the מקוה mikvah that she's going to
in order to be with her husband. אי איהו קדים ומשמש, Ee
hu kadim umishamesh, if he after this event of them bumping into
one another, אי איהו, ee hu, right?
אי איהו, ee hu, he. Right, I thought I said that. Okay.
No.
If he has sex first, goes back home has sex with his
wife, she goes home has sex with her husband, so if he's
the one that has sex first,
אחתא ליה לדידיה רוח זנונים, achda lei l'didei ruach znunim, a spirit
presumably like a demon of licentiousness takes hold of him. מאי
תקנתיה Mai takantei which will obviously lead him to sin. So, I'm
sorry did I skip a line? Yeah, I skipped a line. אי
איהו קדים ומשמש אחתא ליה לדידיה רוח זנונים. Ee hu kadim umishamesh
achda lei l'didei ruach znunim. אי איהי קדמה ומשמשא, Ee hee kadma
umishamsha, if she has sex first, אחתא לה לדידה רוח זנונים. achda
lah l'didah ruach znunim. So a spirit or a demon of licentiousness
takes hold of her. So מאי תקנתיה mai takanteh what's the fix
of this? לימא הכי lema hachi say the following. שפוך בוז על
נדיבים shfoch buz al nedivim that God pours out disgrace on the
princes וישגם בתוהו לא דרך vayashgem betohu lo darech makes them wander
in the desolate areas without a path. So maybe somehow that that
means that the shed should depart from you God should God should
whatever attack him and it should depart.
Let's look at Tosafot right away.
Right away. Tosafot, if you flip back one page, it was printed
on the previous page on קז עמוד א. kuf zayin amud alef.
Tosafot quotes the very famous Gemara that Rabbi Yochanan intentionally would do
this. So if you take a look at the Tosafot הימנת דפגע
באיתתא haiman depaga be-itata Tosafot says בהא דאמרי בנסיה מתא be-ha de-amri
bi-nessia mesa Rabbi Yochanan רב יוחנן הוה קאזיל ויתיב אשערי טבילה Rav
Yochanan hava ka-azil ve-yasiv a-sharei tevila Rabbi Yochanan would sit by the
gates near the near
the mikvah היכי דלדון זרעא דכוותיה heichi dileyaldun zara de-chavateih that the
women, he was very handsome, very beautiful, Rabbi Yochanan, and the Gemara
has this idea out that what the man and or the woman
are thinking about at the moment of conception impacts the nature of
the child. Okay, so what they're actually what's images that are going
through their heads at that moment affects what they're having sex and
that the they're conceiving affects what the child will be.
So Rabbi Yochanan wants them to look like him.
Yes, so Rabbi Yochanan, right, so Rabbi Yochanan was so handsome, he
thought, I'm going to do a favor for all these women, they'll
look at me on their way home to their husbands, they'll be
thinking, interestingly, thinking of me when they're having sex with their husband,
or maybe it helped that they thought about him beforehand. I don't
and then the children will be handsome and good-looking children. So the
Gemara says, so Tosafot's got a problem. He says, you're not how
about this Gemara that if you bump into a woman, then you're
going to be seized, you or she will be seized with this
demon of licentiousness? So the Gemara says, הכא דפגע באישעתא דסלקא מן
המים. hacha depaga beshata desalka min hamayim. No, our concern is the
minute she gets out of the water as opposed to Rabbi Yochanan
maybe he's naked. You know, Rabbi Yochanan was talking about about a
few minutes later when she already came out of the mikvah, she
was dressed, she was going to the gates. Okay.
רב יוחנן אשערי
טבילה יתיב. Rav Yochanan a-sharei tevila yasiv. אי נמי i nami he
says, התם יתיב הכא פגע. hatam yasiv hacha paga. It's one thing
where you were sitting, the other is where you bumped into her.
I guess you both are walking and you more directly bump in,
maybe seeing at a distance as opposed to directly confronting. אי נמי
i nami third answer, רב יוחנן הוה אמר Rav Yochanan hava amar
שפוך בוז על נדיבים. shfoch buz al nedivim. He says a pasuk.
Of course, what about her? Let's say she had sex first. She
probably would have had sex first because he's sitting there the whole
night I guess. I don't know. Anyway,
so very that's a challenging Gemara in itself, also because if seeing
him makes her think about him, then isn't that a problem that
she's thinking about Rabbi Yochanan when they're having sex with her husband?
All right, back to the Gemara. אמר רב יצחק. amar Rav Yitzchak.
So said Rabbi Yitzchak. מאי דכתיב mai de-chtiv what's meant by the
pasuk, גם כי אלך בגיא צלמות לא אירא רע כי אתה עמדי
gam ki elech be-gei tzalmavet lo ira ra ki ata imadi when
I go in the valley of the shadow of death. What is
the valley of the shadow of death? What is this place that
is
so vulnerable to danger, so exposed to danger? So the Gemara says,
זה הישן בצל דקל יחידי ze hayashen betzel dekel yechidi back to
the palm trees. If you're sleeping in the shade of a single
palm tree, that's a place where shedim like to hang out. And
notice again, בצל betzel like בגיא צלמות. be-gei tzalmavet. So places where
shade is a danger. ובצל לבנה u-vetzel levana the shade of the
moon. So if there's a moon out and then you're in a
place that is that the moonlight hits and then you're at the
other side of the wall that's provided that's shaded from that moon,
that's considered the moon shade.
ובצל דקל יחידי לא אמרן u-vetzel dekel yechidi lo amaran the danger
of a single palm tree we only said, אלא דלא נפל טולא
דחבריה עלויה ela dela nafal tula de-chavreih alaveih it's not overlapped with
the shade of another tree. Okay, so it's not just that it's
standing alone, but the shade is only the shade of that tree.
אבל נפל טולא דחבריה עלויה לית לן בה aval nafal tula de-chavreih
alaveih leit lan bah if the shade of its fellow, of another
palm tree overlapped with it, it's not a problem. אלא הא דתניא
ela ha de-tanya so now the Gemara sort of gets into its
halakhic language, and that which we taught in a brayta, הישן בצל
דקל יחידי בחצר. hayashen betzel dekel yechidi be-chatzer. We have a brayta
that says that it's specifically a problem in a courtyard because a
courtyard presumably also there's it's less open so there's less room for
the shade to move around, so there's a higher danger in a
courtyard. והישן בצל לבנה דמו בראשו ve-hayashen betzel levana damo be-rosho or
in the shade of moon shade your blood is on your head.
היכי דמי heichi dami what's the case of courtyard because we just
said now that it was a problem even in the open field?
אילימא דלא נפל טולא דחבריה עלויה ilima dela nafal tula de-chavreih alaveih
if it's not overlapped, אפילו בשדה נמי afilu be-sadeh nami even in
the field the shade would be a problem. אלא לאו ela lav
must be if we're heightening the problem in a courtyard, שמע מינה
בחצר אף על גב דנפל טולא דחבריה עלויה shma mina be-chatzer af
al gav de-nafal tula de-chavreih alaveih it's a problem even when the
shade falls overlaps with it because that's the special problem of the
courtyard. I have to tell you with all these Gemaras to me
what's... I think is like, is particularly disturbing is when it uses
this type of a discourse, right? Because it makes you, look I
understand that's the way they talked and they analyzed this material, but
it basically all seems to send the message that they're sort of
seeing these issues, I'm not saying it's true, but it leaves you
with a feeling that they're weighing these types of discussions and issues
the same way they weigh the halakhic material. Ah, we got a
ברייתא baraita this way, we got a ברייתא baraita that way, must
be with up in this case as opposed to that case. Now
then, it could just be that's the language that they use to
deal with, you know, and they, so it's borrowed language, but it
does, I think, raise a question about what weight they're assigning to
these types of discussions.
Yeah, so two things. One, when, when the language shifts its rhetorical
valence like that, right, how do we know what the tone is?
Maybe they're being playful.
Ah, that could be. That could be.
Right, it's very hard
to tell when they're being, right. And I also wondered whether, I
also wondered whether it was like, could be like a later layer,
you know, and the whole question about who are the people that
are saying this, all this is anonymous, right?
And that's why I say that. And the second thing is a
very naive question. Did the ancients think that the moon was a
direct source of light? As opposed to reflective, so they had a
concept of moonlight and sunlight and moon shade.
Right. Yeah, that's an interesting question.
Well, it starts early, רש״י Rashi's בראשית. Bereishit.
Yeah, about the moon, the lesser light. Yeah, they seem to suggest
the idea, you know,
מאורות, meorot, you know. But yes, I think that's a good point.
I do think that the material seems to suggest that, that it
is, it is seen as its own light. I'm sure we could
easily find the answer to that question.
Yes. And it's important to remember that this was centuries before the
germ theory of disease, for example.
Clearly, right.
So they needed to come up with some rationale for why people
got sick. Right. And aside from the blatant superstitions, right, they found
that people who went into dark crowded areas to relieve themselves where
other people had gone to relieve themselves got sick. Right.
So, right, I think you're absolutely correct. Look, you have this when
the גמרא gemara deals with an issue about מים מגולים, mayim megulim,
exposed water, right, which might have been, there might have been real
issues there about bacteria and other things, but so the גמרא gemara
saw maybe some correlation of exposed water to sickness and interpreted it
as a snake is leaving poison behind, right? But it's exactly trying
to, trying to see some order and give some explanation and maybe
even find some degree of correlation to certain things, but just with
wrong interpretations, you know?
And it could be that, you know, maybe the demons would want
to avoid public areas like that. Area is busy, hanging out there.
Right, although you do wonder, right? Because in public is where more
germs are spread. So anyway, alright. Alright, moving on. שמע מינה. shma
mina. It's a good point. We see that in the חצר chatzer
it's a problem even with overlapping shade. ובצילא של לבנה לא אמרן,
u-v'tzila shel levana lo amran, the shade of a moon we only
said this, אלא במערבה, ella b'ma'arava, only when the shade is being
cast to the west. So apparently, I don't know, I haven't paid
attention to this. I don't know if we have any amateur astronomers
among us. But the רשב״ם Rashbam says that at the end of
the night, the moon is in the east, so the shade would
be cast to the west if there's a wall and the moon's
in the east and the moon's sitting here, right? So then the
shade is being cast to the west of the wall. So that's
only a problem when you're sitting in shade that's being cast to
the west. אבל במדנחא, aval b'madnacha,
the east, the beginning of the night where the moon's in, I
don't think the moon moves in the night, does it? Moves during,
it does? It moves all night?
Really? Moves about 40. Every hour it's a different position?
Aha.
No, from night to night it moves, but does it in the
course of a night does it move?
And not only that, it tips different angles. Or is it, it
also rotates.
I am not a good observer of the moon. Interesting. So let's
finish this line. He says, so anyway, so the רשב״ם Rashbam says
at the beginning of the night where the moon is in the
east and, and the moon is in the west and the shade
is in the east, if you have a wall, לית לן בה,
leit lan bah, you're in the east shade, it's not a problem.
Yes. I have no idea. What did you want to say?
Every day it's about 40
minutes, each, it raises
40 minutes, about 40 minutes later each day. Uh-huh. So some, right.
And sometimes in the beginning of the
day it'll be, right, sometimes the moon rises in the daytime, right,
even. Right. Okay. Alright, now, האי מן דמפני, hai man d'mafni,
now קא ע״ב, kof aleph amud bet, a person that relieves himself,
אגידדא דדיקלא, agidda d'dikla, on a,
once again with the palm trees, on a stump of a palm
tree, אחתיה לדידיה רוח פלגא, achtei l'didei ruach palga,
he is seized with the spirit of the, רוח ruach here's again
like the demon פלגא. palga. Might be the name of a demon.
רשב״ם Rashbam seems to say also that it's some type of a,
of a disease, maybe some type of a disease that affects his,
you know, his, you know, his bottom. Did they say paralysis?
Paralysis is what they say?
Okay, paralyze them.
At least Winters.
Uh-huh, right. האי מן דמצלי רישא אגידדא דדיקלא, hai man d'matzli reisha
agidda d'dikla, and if you lean over the trunk of a palm
tree, אחתיה רוח צרדא, achtei ruach tzrada, so then the demon צרדא
tzrada takes hold of you. But צרדא tzrada also refers to a
type of a migraine headache. So there it is connected to the,
you know. To maybe the head which is leaning over. האי מאן
דפסיע אדיקלא Hai man d'pasia adikla a person who steps over presumably
a cut-down palm tree. Really all the stuff with palm trees, the
שדים shedim really like them. אם מקטע קטלו im mikta katlo if
the palm tree has been cut down, then you'll be murdered. אי
עקר ee yakar if the palm tree just naturally fell down, מעקר
ומית miakar umayas then you'll die. I guess it means soon, we're
all going to die. הני מילי דלא מנח כרעי עילויה Hani mili
dilo manach karei ilavei but that's only if you didn't rest your
leg on it as you were walking over. You stepped over it
with one step.
אבל מנח כרעי עילויה Aval manach karei ilavei if you rest your
leg on the palm tree that you're stepping over, לית לן בה
leis lan bah it's not a problem. No, I guess not. Okay,
yes.
What's the question? מצלי matzli you said lean over. מצלי matzli in
another context to pray. So is that the base meaning, that is
to say to lean over?
That's a good question.
Like ברוך Baruch or הודאה hodaah is to bend your knee.
That's a fascinating question. Yeah, I don't know. A combination of leaning,
a theological dimension
to the base meaning of the word to pray.
It's a good question. You could check Jastrow or the other
dictionary, what's-his-name, the new one, Sokoloff I think. Yeah, so there's
some... but that's an excellent point, the מצלי matzli and the תפילה.
tefillah. Okay, חמישה טולי הוי הוו. Chamisha tulei havi havu. There are
five dangerous shades.
טולא דדיקלא יחידא tula d'dikla yechida as we mentioned, the shade of
a single palm tree. טולא דכנדא tula d'kanda the shade of a
כנדא kanda which is another type of a tree. טולא דפרחא tula
d'parcha the shade of a פרחא parcha which is like more of
a plant. What do they translate פרחא? parcha?
What? I don't know. Caper bush. טולא דזרזתא tula d'zarjeta and the
shade of a זרזתא zarjeta which is a what?
Sorb tree. Sorb tree. There you go. Now of course if you're
counting, that was four not five. So some switch the גירסא girsa
to
ארבעה טולי הוו. arba tulei havu. Okay, איכא דאמרי Ika d'amri some
say אף טולא דארבא af tula d'arba the shade of a boat.
וטולא דערבתא v'tula d'arveta or the shade of a willow.
כללא דמילתא klala d'milsa the general rule is כל דנפיש ענפיה kol
dinapish anfei anything that has a lot of branches קשי טוליה kashi
tulei its shade is dangerous. וכל דקשי סילואיה v'kol d'kashi silvayei and
anything that it's the wood is hard, it might be means has
thorns or is hard קשי טוליה kashi tulei it also its shade
is dangerous.
לבר מקרומשה Levar mikarumashe with the exception of this tree קרומשה. karumashe.
How do they translate קרומשה? karumashe?
The English I looked at said service tree. I've never heard of
a service tree. What did they say there?
Not translated here.
Not translated. Okay. Service tree? What? This is a service tree? I
have no idea what that means. Anyway, I always think of ערבות
aravos
and הדסים hadasim because you're not supposed to like
don't stay in the shade when you're cutting down the הדס hadas
the you know, exactly, the ערבות aravos for your לולב. lulav. אף
על גב דקשי סילואיה af al gav d'kashi silvayei this tree, even
though it's got a hard wood, לא קשי טוליה lo kashi tulei
its shade is not dangerous. Why? דאמרה ליה שידא לברה D'amrah lei
sheida livrah שידא sheida which was one of the names of the
שדים shedim said to her
daughter פרחי נפשך מקרומשה pirchi nafshach mikrumashe fly away from קרומשה, karumashe,
don't stay under the shade of that tree, דאיהו דקטל לאבוך d'ihu
d'katol la'avuch that it's what killed your father. So there's gotta have
been some myth out there about how whatever one of the שדים
shedim had an interaction with this tree and it killed him.
וקטל לדידי v'katol l'didei and it also wound up killing... killing her
son. So even though she gave him this advice presumably. So anyway,
so therefore שדים shedim avoid this tree so you're safe. Yes.
This whole pun is much better in English because you're talking about
the shade where the shady are. Right.
I know, I was going to mention that. I was going to
mention that point.
And just
as a small linguistic point, I think that טולא tula means shade,
so when you have in the ברייתות baraitos לטייל
בסוכה letayel basukkah it means to go in the shade. That's a
fascinating question, is לטייל letayel from also the idea of being in
the shade? Very fascinating. Thank you. Okay. אמר רב אשי חזינא ליה
לרב כהנא דפריש מכולהו טולי Amar Rav Ashi: Chazivna l'Rav Kahana d'parish
mikulu tulei I saw that רב כהנא Rav Kahana avoided all shades.
Okay, now, בי פרחא רוחי bei parchi ruchi the spirit, the name
of the spirit that lives under in this פרחא parcha tree, whatever
we said that was, is named רוחי. ruchi. דבי זרזתא d'bei zarjeta
the one that lives in זרזתא zarjeta what was that, a sorb
tree, is called שידא. sheida. דבי אגרי d'bei igri the spirit that
lives on rooftops is called רישפי. rishpi. רשפי אש רשפי. rishpei esh
rishpei. Right, oh yeah. Yeah, I know.
למאי נפקא מינה? L'mai nafka mina?
Now here comes a new idea. What do I care what their
names are? לקמיעא. Likmiya. So when you write an amulet, you know
to direct the amulet, somebody's having trouble because of this encounter or
because when they go up to the roof, things happen, you write
a קמיעא, kmiya, you have to know the names of the שדים
shedim that you are directing it to. דבי פרחי, De-bei parchi, בריה
שאין לה עיניים, birya she-ein la einayim, this the spirit of דבי
פרחי De-bei parchi of this tree is one that has no eyes.
למאי נפקא מינה, L'mai nafka mina, what do I care it doesn't
have eyes? לגזוזי לה, Ligzuzei lah, to run away from it. Okay,
is that it won't be able to follow you. זימנא חדא הוה
אזיל צורבא מרבנן לאתנויי לבי פרחי, zimna chada havay azil tzurva m'rabanan
l'itnuyei l'vei parchi, one there was a time where a certain Torah
student went to relieve himself in this פרחי parchi tree and he
went under the shade which is of course dangerous. שמע דקא אתי
לגביה, Shama d'ka ati laveih, he heard that the spirit was coming
to attack him, I don't know, he heard rustling in the leaves.
וגזילא, Vegazilei, and he ran away from it and he was safe
because
because it doesn't have eyes it couldn't follow him. Okay, כי אזל
ki azil as he was going חבטיה לדיקלא, chavtei l'dikla, we had
this before when somebody was being attacked by witchcraft, he grabbed hold
to a palm tree, again the palm trees are all associated as
we've seen with these concerns. צווח דיקלא, Tzavach dikla, the palm tree
cried out,
ופקע היא upaka hi and it burst. What burst? The tree? The
shade? Some say it means the shade burst, the demon burst. I
don't know. Okay. Do your English interpretation do your Englishes say shrivelled
or cried out for the palm tree? Anybody has other translations? Cried
out. Cried out? Really? Interesting. צווח. Tzavach. Okay.
צווח Tzavach of really yell. Yeah maybe that's צוות tzavat I don't
know anyway. Okay. Now, פרחא דבי זרדתא שידי, pircha d'vei zardeta sheedi,
the spirit of this of the זרדתא zardeta tree I don't know
the caper bush is called שידא sheeda or שידי. sheedi. סדא's Sada
the sorb tree. סדא's Sada the sorb tree, thank you. חזירא דתסמיכא
למתא, Hazira d'tadsameicha l'mata, there's no eyes. Thank you. Right, that's true.
I gotta tell you that story about rustling if that's what it
meant and running away makes me think of the גן עדן Gan
Eden story, right? קול השם אלקים מתהלך בגן Kol Hashem Elokim mithalech
bagan and hiding and running. Anyway, I don't know if that was
intended or not. Anyway,
חזירא דתסמיכא למתא, hazira d'tasamicha l'mata, there was this what was it,
caper bush that was not caper, what was it? Sorb tree that
was near a city. לא פחת משישין שידי. Lo pachas mi-shishin sheedi.
It has no fewer if you have a sorb tree near a
city it has no fewer than sixty demons inhabiting it. למאי נפקא
מינה? L'mai nafka mina? What do I care? למכתב לה קמיעא L'michtav
la kmiya to write a קמיעא, kmiya, you gotta know that you're
attacking a lot of שדים, shedim, not just one. Now we'll have
a story about this. ההוא בר קשיא דמתא, Hahu bar kashya d'mata,
there was a certain officer like head of the city, דאזיל וקאי
גבי זרדתא. d'azil l'kai gabei zardeta. He spent he rested underneath this
sorb tree דהוה סמיך למתא d'havi samich l'mata which was near the
city. עלו ביה שישין שידי, Alu bei shishin sheedi, so sixty שדים
shedim possessed him, ואיסתכן veistaken and his life was in danger. אתא
להו מרבנן, Ata l'hu m'rabanan, he went to a certain one of
the rabbis meaning that's always means like a rabbinic student, דלא ידע
דזרדתא דשישין שידי היא. d'lo yada d'zardeta d'shishin sheedi hi. He didn't
know that the זרדתא zardeta tree had sixty demons inhabiting it. כתב
לה קמיעא לחד שידא. Kesav la kmiya l'chad sheeda. He only wrote
him a קמיעא kmiya to for effective for one שידא. sheid. שמע
דתלו כינגי בגוויה, Shama d'talu chingi be-gavaieh, so then he heard afterwards
that the שדים shedim hung a harp from the tree, וקא משרו
הכי veka mesharru hachi
and they were having like a little dance they were celebrating when
they heard that he wrote a קמיעא kmiya for just one שידא
sheid and this is what they were singing: סודריה דמר כי צורבא
מרבנן, sudreih d'mar ki tzurva m'rabanan, that
that man's handkerchief or because they would wear a cloth around their
head and wrap it that would be like a rabbinic type of
a garb, so the kerchief around his head makes it seem like
he's a rabbi or rabbinic student, בדיקנא ביה דמר badikna bei d'mar
but we actually gave him a פארהער, faher, we checked into him,
דלא ידע ברוך אתה d'lo yada baruch ata and he doesn't even
know how to make a ברכה, bracha, like. So they were making
fun of ברוך, Baruch, דלא ידע ברוך, d'lo yada baruch, right also,
I'm sorry, דלא ידע ברוך, d'lo yada baruch, he doesn't know how
to make a ברכה, bracha, he didn't even know that there was
only one שידא sheid in this tree.
And then this is like
hilarious, hilarious. It has to be in the fun must be happening
at whatever level or dimension this is.
Yeah, yeah, you'd hope so. אתא ההוא מרבנן דידע, Ata hahu m'rabanan
d'yada, so then came another rabbinic student who
knew, דזרדתא דשישין שידי הוה, d'zardeta d'shishin sheedi hava, that in this
זרדתא zardeta there were sixty שדים. shedim. כתב לה קמיעא דשישין שידי.
Kesav la kmiya d'shishin sheedi. So he wrote a קמיעא kmiya that
was effective against sixty שדים. shedim. שמע דקא אמרי, Shama d'ka amri,
then he heard that they were saying, I don't know who the
שמע shama is, the officer who was possessed, anyway, פנו מנייכו מהכא,
panu m'naichu me-hacha, remove your vessels from here because they had to
all leave because they were being chased out by this. But again
these גמרות Gemaras clearly you know. Both reflect the reality that people
were writing קמיעות *kameas* but also reinforce it, and we know that
קמיעות *kameas* was very widespread till even a few hundred years ago,
even today people
will go to people for קמיעות *kameas*.
Okay, so now the גמרא *Gemara* continues. Let's do just one more
piece. קטב מרירי *Ketev Meriri*, which is referred to in the תורה
*Torah* and in the גמרא *Gemara* associates here with a type of
demonic spirit. So תרי קטבי הוו *trei katvei havei*, there are two
of these קטבס *Ketevs* because... so חד מקמי טיהרא *chad mikamei tihara*,
one that roams around before noon, וחד מבתר טיהרא *v'chad mibatar tihara*,
and one afternoon. דמקמי טיהרא *d'mikamei tihara*, the one that roams around
before noon, קטב מרירי שמו *Ketev Meriri shemo*, its name is קטב
מרירי *Ketev Meriri*. And now we don't know why you need to
know the names.
ומחזי בכדא דכמחא *umachzi
b'kada d'kamcha*, it appears like in a vessel of a type of
a puls, of a type of a compound where the mortar, wait,
no, I'm sorry, in the mortar where the pestle is moving around
in it. I have no idea what that means. How do they
describe that? What does your English say for this?
Here, well, it's in this כמחא *kamcha* which was a whole thing
that we have before, right, and some sort of dipping sauce, right.
And does this just where it lives or this is how it
appears? It appears like the look of this
in a jug of כמחא *kamcha*.
Okay, it appears in a jug of כמחא *kamcha* when you're banging
around with the pestle. As the whirling mixing spoon. Okay, oh, maybe
that. It appears like a spoon.
So it appears in
this and it looks like it appears. Okay, that's okay, I hear
that. Error. It so it appears in this, in this vessel and
it looks like a stirring spoon. Okay. So now where are we?
Okay, who knows? Let's just finish this. דבתר טיהרא *d'batar tihara*, the
one that appears after noon, קטב ישוד צהרים שמו *Ketev Yashud Tzahorayim
shemo*, its name is קטב ישוד צהרים *Ketev Yashud Tzahorayim*, right, we
see in תהילים *Tehillim*, and there you have צהרים *tzahorayim*, the afternoon.
ומחזי בקרנא דעיזא *umachzi b'karna d'iza*, it can be it appears between
the horns of goats, והדר ביה כנפיא *v'hadar bei knafaya*, and wings
surround it.
But here it says it appears in the midst of horns of
goats as a whirling sieve.
A whirling sieve?
Really?
Okay, other translations of this are totally that it's surrounded by wings
or by feathers. אביי הוה שקיל ואזיל *Abaye hava shakil v'azil*, one
story about this, אביי *Abaye* was going ואזיל ורב פפא מימיניה ורב
הונא בריה דרב יהושע משמאליה *v'azil v'Rav Papa miymineh v'Rav Huna breih
d'Rav Yehoshua mismaleh*, Rav Papa on his right and Rav Huna breih
d'Rav Yehoshua on his left. חזיה לההוא קטב מרירי *chazya l'hahu Ketev
Meriri*, he saw the קטב מרירי *Ketev Meriri* דקאתי לאפיה *d'ka ati
l'apei* that was coming towards him. So what did he do? לאפיה
דשמאליה *l'apei d'smaleh*, it was coming towards his left side. So אהדריה
לרב פפא לשמאליה *ahadrei l'Rav Papa l'smaleh*, so he moved Rav Papa
to the left, ולרב הונא בריה דרב יהושע לימיניה *v'l'Rav Huna breih
d'Rav Yehoshua liyamineh* to the right. So אמר ליה רב פפא *amar
leh Rav Papa*, so Rav Papa said to him, you didn't want
to be on this rabbi's bad side because he... anyway, so Rav
Papa said to him, אנא מאי שנא דלא חשישת לי *ana mai
shna d'lo chashasht li*, why are you not concerned for me when
if the shade's going to encounter me, right? So אמר ליה את
שעתא קיימא לך *amar leh at sha'ata kayama lach*, you, it's a
good time for you, meaning you're very wealthy and you have a
lot of מזל *mazel* clearly from, so I figured that that מזל
*mazel* would save you from this encounter as well. Okay, what?
So you can rely on that?
So you, I don't know. Let's just one more thing. מחד בתמוז
עד שיתסר ביה *michad b'Tammuz ad shitser beh*, now this is interesting
because it's proximity to the three weeks and there is discussion how
some of the practices around the three weeks might have been influenced
by some of these beliefs at this time in the year anyway
was exposed to some of these dangers. So from the first of
תמוז *Tammuz* to the sixteenth to right before the three weeks to
שבעה עשר בתמוז *Shiva Asar B'Tammuz*, ודאי שכיחי *vadai sh'chichi*, these קטב
מרירי *Ketev Meriri* powers are definitely very prevalent. מכאן ואילך ספק שכיחי
ספק לא שכיחי *mikan v'eilach safek sh'chichi safek lo sh'chichi*, from that
point on maybe they're somewhat prevalent. ומשתכחי בטולי דחצבא דלא חצבי גרמידא
*u'mishtakchei b'tulei d'chatzva d'lo chatzvei garmida*,
they can be found in the shade of a חצבא *chatzva*, what's
a חצבא *chatzva* again? Type of grass. A grass, right, a type
of a grass that do not grow a אמה *amah* tall. ובטולי
דצפרא ופניא דלא הוי גרמידא *u'btulei d'tzafra v'panya d'lo havei garmida*, and
in the shade of the morning and the afternoon
that it is not a אמה *amah* long that shade. והיקר *v'hikar*,
but its fundamental place where it lodges is בטולי דבית הכסא *b'tulei
d'veit hakissei*, in the shade of a bathroom. I think it's a
good place to stop.
Okay, good place to take a
bathroom break.